A Guide to the Papers of Charles Julian Bishko, 1930-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Charles Julian Bishko 1930-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12710
The collection contains ca. 20,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictiosn
Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisition Information
The collection is a gift from Dr. Charles J. Bishko.
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles Julian Bishko is a noted specialist in Spanish and Portuguese history of the Middle Ages and an international authority on the Iberian background of Latin American history, the history of the medieval frontier, the Reconquista and on Spanish Cluniac Monasticism. He developed this renown during a distinguished career of almost 40 years at the University of Virginia where, through superior teaching methods, meticulous research and scholarly writings, he labored to make the University a focal point for students of early Spanish and Portuguese history.
Dr. Bishko was born in New York City on October 6, 1906. He studied for his A.B. and A.M. degrees in Classics at the University of Syracuse. Later, during the period 1930-1938 at Harvard, he earned the A.M. in ecclesiastical history; served as a University Fellow and a Francis Parkman Fellow; spent a research year in Spain as a Sheldon Traveling Fellow; earned his Ph.D.(1937) with a dissertation on Spanish Monasticism in the Visigothic period and taught history at Radcliffe College.
In 1938, he left Harvard, married Lucretia Ramsey and accepted an appointment at the University of Virginia as an instructor of ancient and medieval history in the (then) Corcoran School. At the University, his career and scholastic reputation developed steadily. He was appointed Professor in 1955 and Commonwealth Professor in 1971. His competence in his field of study and in his teaching skills was recognized by his induction into the Real Academia de la Historica in Madrid in 1974 and by his receipt of the University of Virginia Alumni Distinguished Professor Award in 1968.
Professor Bishko was an active member of the University community and served on many committee and faculty assignments. Of particular note is his work as Secretary of President Shannon's Special Committee on the Admission of Women to the College of Arts and Sciences. (1967-68)
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains ca.20,000 items (11 shelf feet) and consists of a) general correspondence with faculty, students, scholars and friends and personal correspondence with close family members; b) academic papers and class notes of Bishko's graduate study years at Harvard; c) materials on courses, correspondence and professional meetings relating to Spanish Portuguese and Latin American Studies; d) University of Virginia departmental papers including committee assignments, reports, correspondence, personalia, awards and honors, lecture notes, outlines and student gradebooks.
The organization of the collection closely follows the order and folder descriptions used by Dr. Bishko.
Contents List
- I: Correspondence
  - General Correspondence 1941-1970s, (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence 1960-1970, (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence 1969-1971, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence 1972-1977, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence and Academica 1949-1969, (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - General Correspondence and Academica 1966-1974, (7 folders) (Box 6)
  - General Correspondence and Academica 1975-1982, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - General Correspondence and Academica 1983-1985, (5 folders) (Box 8)
  - General Correspondence and Academica 1986-1989, (6 folders) (Box 9)
  - Correspondence with Dr. Edwin (Ed) Popper, New York City 1950s-1980s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with Miss Ramona L. Bishko, Syracuse, New York 1950s-1980s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with with Editor, Prof. Sylvia Thrupp, Comparative Studies in Society and History 1957-1958 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with with Prof. Gary Dunbar, UCLA--Geography 1958-1970 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with External and Intra University 1960s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with with Claudio Sanchez-Albornoz and Hilda Grassotti. Plus Correspondence re Claudio's, Espana Enigma Historica1960s-1970s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with Student--Graduate and Undergraduate 1960s-1970s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with with Prof. Lewis Hanke and Family 1960s-1980s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with with Prof. Charles R. Boxer, University of London 1963-1964 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence--with Graduate Students--Memorabilia re: Oral Exams, Job Recommendations, etc. for Graduate Students 1964-1976 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence with with Prof. Antonio Henrique de Oliveira Marques,University of Lisbon, Portugal 1965-1966 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence General--Plus Material re: Fifth Conference on Medieval Studies, Kalamazoo, Mich., May 1970 1968-1970 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence During Preparation of Doctoral Dissertations with Doctoral Students--R. Pride [1970]-1973 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence During Preparation of Doctoral Dissertations with Doctoral Students--James Brodman [1970]-1976 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence During Preparation of Doctoral Dissertations with Doctoral Students--Lawrence J. McCrank 1970-1976 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence During Preparation of Doctoral Dissertations with Doctoral Students--Lorna Jury Gladstone [1971-1977] (Box 11)
  - Correspondence During Preparation of Doctoral Dissertations with Doctoral Students--Thomas C. Thurston [1974] (Box 11)
  - Correspondence During Preparation of Doctoral Dissertations with Doctoral Students--Heath Dillard [1975]-1979 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence During Preparation of Doctoral Dissertations with Doctoral Students--James F. Powers 1976-1977 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence During Preparation of Doctoral Dissertations with Doctoral Students--M.C. Fernandez [1976]-1977 (Box 11)
  - A: Family Correspondence
    - Charles Julian Bishko to Lucretia 1930-1933, (8 folders) (Box 12)
    - Charles Julian Bishko to Lucretia 1934-1938, (7 folders) (Box 13)
    - Lucretia to Charles Julian Bishko 1930-1934, (8 folders) (Box 14)
    - Lucretia to Charles Julian Bishko 1934-1941, (7 folders) (Box 15)
    - Bishko Family and Miscellany 1931-1988, (6 folders) (Box 16)
- II: Harvard Graduate School of Arts and Sciences: Class Notes on Courses
  - Student Paper--Charles Julian Bishko, History 8, "A Study of the History of Anjou" 1930 (Box 17)
  - The History of France to 1461, Offered by Prof. Charles Holt Taylor, Session of 1930-1931, Fall Term 1930-1931 (Box 17)
  - English Constitutional History, Offered by Prof. Charles Howard McIlwain, Session of 1930-1931 1930-1931 (Box 17)
  - History of Political Theory, offered by Prof. C.H. McIlwain, Session of 1930-1931 (pp.21-80); Concluding Portion of History of Modern Germany, Prof. S.B. Fay, Session of 1931-1932 (pp. 97-190) 1930-1931 (Box 17)
  - Hist. 6 Medieval Intellectual History--Prof. C.H. Taylor; History Medieval Italy, Prof. George LaPiana; Seminar on Medieval Monasticism, Prof. George LaPiana; History 9: English Const., C.H. McIlwain 1930-1932 (Box 17)
  - Prof. George LaPiana, Session of 1930-1931, The Medieval Church From Gregory I To Gregory VII(pp. 2-189); Christian Institutions(pp 195-410), Session of 1931-1932 1930-1932 (Box 18)
  - The History of Modern Germany, Offered by Sidney Bradshaw Fay, Session of 1931-1932 1931-1932 (Box 18)
    (continued in pp. 97-162 of separate volume with McIlwain, Pol. Theory)
  - Research Year in Spain as Sheldon Traveling Fellow (Memorabilia) 1933-1934 (Box 18)
- III: Spain--Portugal--Latin America: Courses, Correspondence, Professional Meetings, Related Material
  - Latin American Studies--Text and Materials for Edition of 16th Century Treatise: Pedro Malferit (d. 1566), De Bello Inferendo Et Conferendis Legibus Hominibus Novi Orbis(Spain's Title to, and Just War in, The New World), Sent Charles Julian Bishko by Prof.Lewis Hanke [1936] (Box 19)
  - Correspondence with Prof. Lewis Hanke, University of Texas [1938,1949-1956] (Box 19)
  - Latin American History (1947-1953), History 11: Colonial Era; History 12: National Era. (First UVA Course in Latin American History, Dept. of History) ca.1947-1953 (Box 19)
  - Latin American Studies (Extracurricular Activities), Weekly Radio Talks on Latin America by Charles Julian Bishko, 1948. (Series 13 Commentaries via U.Va. Radio Station) 1948 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence with Prof. Lewis Hanke [1948-1971] (Box 19)
  - Spanish and Latin American Studies, 1955-1967--Correspondence: with Editors, Hispanic American Hist. Rev., Amer. Hist. Rev.; with Individuals; Materials on Conference on Latin American History, American Historical Association. [1949]-1967 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence with Hispanic American Historical Review and Other Related Materials on Latin American History ca.1950-1970 (Box 19)
  - American Historical Association--Annual Meeting, 1953, Chicago, (Correspondence on Session Participation) 1953 (Box 20)
  - Review Materials, with Ensuing Correspondence: C.M. Lewis, S.J. and A.J. Loomis, S.J, "The Spanish Jesuit Mission in Virginia, 1570-1572," Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, 1951 [1953-1954] (Box 20)
  - American Historical Review--Correspondence Regarding Quarterly Bibliography Section Spain and Portugal 1954-1961 (Box 20)
  - American Historical Association--Annual Meeting, 1955, Washington, D.C.--Correspondence Relating to Session on Medieval History 1955 (Box 20)
  - Latin American Studies--Program on the History of America, 1956; Conference on Latin American History, 1966 1956,[1967] (Box 20)
  - American Historical Association-- American Historical Review--Correspondence Relating to Quarterly Spanish-Portuguese Bibliography Section, A.H.R. [1957]-1973 (Box 20)
  - Paper, with Related Materials, Presented to: Second International Congress of Historians of U.S. and Mexico, Austin, Texas, Nov., 1958--"The Castilian as Plainsman" 1958 (Box 20)
  - Prince Henry the Navigator and the Portuguese Discoveries, (1) Quincentenary of 1960: Exhibit in Alderman Library by Charles Julian Bishko with Prof. Gary Dunbar and William Runge, 1960; (2) Charles Julian Bishko Evaluation of MS Book by Prof. Bailey Diffie, Portugal Overseas Before 1415, 1959 1959-1960 (Box 20)
  - Lecture: "The Spanishness of Roman Spain" (Presented to U.Va. Classics Club, 27 March 1961) 1961 (Box 20)
  - Latin American Studies--Correspondence 1969-1970 [1962-1964] (Box 20)
  - Appraisal for Rockefeller Foundation of MS Book by Antonio Antelo, Documentos Para La Historia De La Cultura, 1963--Related Correspondence 1963 (Box 20)
  - Papers Relating to Lecture by Prof. Philippe Wolff, University of Toulouse--"Medieval Catalonia" 1963 (Box 20)
  - American Historical Association--Service as Member Program Committee; AHA Annual Meeting, 1964; Correspondence and Related Materials 1964, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Latin American Studies--Correspondence, 1965-1966, Relating to Fourth Centenary of Fray Bartolome' De Las Casas 1965-1966 (Box 21)
  - Organizing Committee on, and Center for, Latin American Studies, College of Arts and Sciences 1965-1969 (Box 21)
  - Extracurricular Activities--Sixth International Colloqium on Luso-Brazilian Studies, 1966, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. And in New York City, Hispanic Society of America, Columbia University. Materials on Attendance 1966 (Box 21)
  - American Historical Association--Annual Meeting, 1966, Session on "The City in Spanish and Portuguese History"--Charles Julian Bishko Discussant 1966 (Box 21)
  - Chapter, "The Spanish and Portuguese Reconquest, 1095-1492" in K.M. Setton, Ed., A History of the Crusades, Madison, Wisc., 1975: vol. III, 396-456--Correspondence with vol. III Editor, H.W. Hazard, 1972-74 1967-1974 (Box 21)
  - Early Medieval Spain--Correspondence Regarding MSS on Early Medieval Galicia of Prof. Harold Livermore, University of British Columbia 1968 (Box 21)
  - American Historical Association--Conference on Latin American History: Preparation of Iberian and African Antecedents Section: Editorial Contribution to Latin America: A Guide to the Historical Literature(Austin, Texas, 1971) 1971 (Box 21)
  - Conference on Latin American History, 1972; 1971 Bolton Prize Committee, Charles Julian Bishko Chairman; Correspondence, etc. 1971-[1973] (Box 22)
  - Ier Congreso De Historica De Andalucia--Correspondence Regarding Paper Presentation, "The Andalusian Municipal Mestas in the 14th and 16th Centuries" plus Programs 1976 (Box 22)
  - American Historical Association, Annual Meeting, 1976, Session on "The Spanish Nobility in the Early Modern Period"--Chaired by Charles Julian Bishko 1976 (Box 22)
  - Extracurricular Activities--Lecture by John H. Elliot, March, 1977, "Olivares: Spanish Statesman"--Elliot, then Prof. Princeton Institute Advanced Studies; Secretly Elected Regius Professor Modern History, Oxford University, (Organized, Presided Over, by Charles Julian Bishko) 1976-1977 (Box 22)
  - Society for Spanish and Portuguese Historical Studies--Chairmanship Session on "Interculturation in Medieval Spain"--Baltimore, 8-9 April, 1976, plus Related Items (1976-78) plus Academy of American Research Historians on Medieval Spain 1976-1978 (Box 22)
  - Book: Spanish and Portuguese Monastic History, 600-1300, Published by Variorum Reprints, London, 1984--Correspondence with John Smedley, Editor, and Related Materials 1982-1985 (Box 22)
  - Evaluation of MS of Book, Alfonso VI, by Prof. Bernard Reilly, 1985-1986 (Box 22)
- IV: University of Virginia: Committee Assignments, Final Reports and Related Materials
  - College of Arts and Sciences--Institute For Research in the Social Sciences; Current Research Plans, Applications, Grants to Charles Julian Bishko 1938-1964 (Box 23)
  - University of Virginia--World War II--Civil Defense, 1942, Fourth Zone, Precinct 2: Charlottesville Area including University Ave. to Rugby Rd., to Virginia Ave.,to 10th St., to University Ave. Charles Julian Bishko and A.P. Fernbach, Wardens in Charge; Post at 10 Elliewood Ave. (esp. Blackout Trials) 1942-[1943], (2 folders) (Box 23)
  - College of Arts and Sciences--Pre Meteorological Training Program, 1943, World War II--U.S. Air Force Detachment, General Materials; Charles Julian Bishko Section Notes 1943 (Box 23)
  - Committee on Organization of Department of Foreign Affairs 1944-1945 (Box 23)
  - Curriculum Reform, 1944, Program and Papers of Faculty "Young Turks" Group of Reformers 1944,[1947] (Box 23)
  - Committee on Status of Department of Geography; General Materials; Correspondence with Prof. Gary Dunbar (Geog.),then in Nigeria [1947,1961]-1966 (Box 23)
  - Report of the Athletic Committee, "The Gooch Report" 1951 (Box 23)
  - Material Relating to Faculty Meeting Debates, to Faculty Council Replacing Faculty Meeting--Extended Remarks Charles Julian Bishko to Faculty (1954); Related Materials 1953-1957 (Box 23)
  - University of Virginia--Miscellaneous Official Publications [1953-1985] (Box 24)
  - College of Arts and Sciences--Dean William Duran's Special Committee on Charge of Plagiarism against Member, Dept. of Germanic Languages--Charles Julian Bishko Chairman--[Restricted] 1956 (Box 24)
  - Faculty Self-Study Committee, "The Finger Committee" [1958-1964] (Box 24)
  - The Research Committee, Charles Julian Bishko as Member, Secretary, Chairman 1958-[1977] (Box 24)
  - Services on President's and Deans Committees, University Center in Virginia, Richmond [1960-1962] (Box 24)
  - University of Virginia: Assembly of Professors Committee on Contractual Relations--Confidential Materials [1962-1970], (7 folders). [Restricted] (Box 24)
  - College of Arts and Sciences--Self-Study Evaluation Program, Prof. Frank Finger, Chairman; Charles Julian Bishko Member; Materials and Final Report 1963 (Box 24)
  - University of Virginia--The Senate--Materials Relating to Membership; 1965-1969, 1974-1978 1965-1974 (Box 24)
  - College of Arts and Sciences--Service, Appointment Committee for Professorship of Religion 1966 (Box 24)
  - Services on University Committees--Summer Grants; etc. 1967-1968 (Box 24)
  - University of Virginia--Pres. Shannon's Special Committee on the Admission of Women to the College of Arts and Sciences (1967-1968)--Minutes by Charles Julian Bishko, Secretary; Final Report of Committee, Nov. 1968 1967-1968 (Box 24)
  - Report by Committee on Contractual Relations on the Assembly of Professors, University of Virginia, Concerning Certain Issues Presented in the Case of Professor Lawrence Cranberg, Department of Physics, University of Virginia, Submitted 14 February 1969--[Restricted] [1968]-1969 (Box 24)
  - Report of the Committee on Contractual Relations of the Assembly of Professors Concerning the Issue of Academic Freedom in the Case of Professor Lawrence Cranberg, Department of Physics, Submitted 6 July 1969--[Restricted] 1969 (Box 24)
  - University of Virginia Alumni Association: Distinguished Professor Award Committee, Service as Representative, College of Arts and Sciences--[Restricted] 1970 (Box 24)
  - College of Arts and Sciences--Special Committee Reports 1970 (Box 24)
  - University of Virginia--Pres. Hereford's Resignation from Farmington Country Club, 1976--Papers from Pro-Presidential College Faculty Support Group for Freedom of Choice [1975]-1976 (Box 24)
  - A: Corcoran Department of History: Departmental Records, Correspondence, Personalia, Awards, Honors, Miscellaneous Letters and Papers
    - Corcoran Department of History--History C7 (later 119-120),The Origins of Europe (given various years ca. 1939-1950) 1939-1950 (Box 25)
    - Medieval Academy of America--Service as Councillor, 1951 [1939],1951-[1954] (Box 25)
    - Correspondence and Miscellaneous Papers 1940s-1980s (Box 25)
    - Book: Charting Democracy with Prof. A.P. Fernbach--Correspondence with Publishers, etc. 1947-1951 (Box 25)
    - Corcoran Department of History--Miscellaneous Papers and Correspondence 1950-1970 (Box 25)
    - Communications from Chairmen; Service on Departmental Committees; Reports; Related Correspondence 1953-1976 (Box 25)
    - The Medieval Frontier, Paper Delivered at American Historical Association Annual Meeting, Washington, 18 Dec. 1955; Ensuing Correspondence with Prof. Owen Lattimore, Johns Hopkins University, 1956; J.L.M. Gulley, University College, London, 1958 1955-1959 (Box 25)
    - Corcoran Department of History--Annual Reports on Publications and Research by Charles Julian Bishko plus Other Professional Activities 1957-1975 (Box 25)
    - Appointments Committees--[Restricted] 1960s-1970s (Box 25)
    - Charles Julian Bishko Service on Departmental Appointments Committees--Correspondence, Reports, etc.--[Restricted] 1960s-1970s (Box 25)
    - Southern Historical Association, Annual Meeting, Asheville, N.C.,1963--Correspondence and Related Materials 1961-1964 (Box 25)
    - Contract and Correspondence with John Wiley and Sons, N.Y., Relating to Projected Book: The Frontier in Medieval History1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Corcoran Department of History--Graduate Curriculum Revision Committee, 1970; Committee on Appointments and Promotions, 1972 [1962],1970-1972 (Box 26)
    - Extracurricular Activities--Lecture by Prof. Manning Clark, National University Australia, Canberra. Organized, Presided Over by Charles Julian Bishko, "Australia, Past and Present" 1963 (Box 26)
    - Projected Book: The Frontier in Medieval History--Contract and Termination with John Wiley and Sons, Inc. 1963-1971 (Box 26)
    - Corcoran Department of History--Search for Projected Appointment in Iberian History--[Restricted] 1966-1967 (Box 26)
    - University of Virginia Alumni Association: Distinguished Professor Award to Charles Julian Bishko, May 1968 plus Life Membership, Correspondence Related, etc. 1968 (Box 26)
    - Extracurricular Activities: Talk to Medieval Circle at Inaugural Meeting: 24 October 1968--"The Saint Antoninus Cult at Pamiers and Cluny's Expansion in Spain" 1968 (Box 26)
    - Notes: "Moby Dick in the NA"--The Oceanic Frontier-- 1968 (Box 26)
    - Appointment to University of Virginia Sesquicentennial Associateship [1968],1969-1970 (Box 26)
    - University of Virginia-- The Medieval Circle 1969-1970 (Box 26)
    - Correspondence with Prof. Emilio Saez Sanchez, University of Barcelona and C.S.I.C. plus Related Correspondence with his Student, Srta. Milagros Rivera 1969-1982 (Box 26)
    - Correspondence with Students 1970s, (2 folders)--[Restricted] (Box 26)
    - Correspondence General (1978-1980) plus Student Letters (1970s) 1970s,1978-1980, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - Liberty Hill Subdivision (Albemarle, Va.) vs. University of Virginia--Materials Relating to Proposed Access Road via Deerpath, Bellair-Liberty Hill to Proposed University College at Birdwood 1971 (Box 26)
    - Appointment to Commonwealth Professorship of History, June 1971 (Box 27)
    - George Alfred Henty Collection--Correspondence and Materials,1972-1980. MS of Lecture "Victorian Womanhood in the Boy's Historical Novelist G.A. Henty"--(Presented to the Fortnightly Club, Charlottesville, 9 May 1978) [1971],1972-1980 (Box 27)
    - Corcoran Department of History--Memorial Resolutions Presented to Faculty of Arts and Sciences: Prof. T. Cary Johnson (1972); Prof. Bernard Mayo (1979) 19,721,979 (Box 27)
    - Appointments Committee-[Restricted] 1975 (Box 27)
    - Symposia on Comparative Frontiers--University of Oklahoma 1975-1978 (Box 27)
    - Disposal of Books from Personal Collection [1978],1979-1981 (Box 27)
    - General Correspondence 1978-1980, (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Book: Studies in Medieval Spanish Frontier History, Variorum Reprints: London, 1980--Correspondence with Editor John Smedley, et. al. 1978-1982 (Box 27)
    - Medieval Academy of America-- Speculum; Correspondence with Editor Regarding MSS Critique 1985 (Box 27)
  - B: Corcoran Department of History: History Courses Offered, Lectures, Outlines, Assignments, Gradebooks
    - Corcoran Department of History--Class Gradebooks--[Restricted] 1938-1948 (Box 28)
    - Lectures and Related Materials from History B 5-6,9,10: Ancient History 1938-ca.1962, (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - History 3-4(B1) Medieval History, Sessions 1938-ca.1965; History HIEU 224, Thought and Society in the High Middle Ages, 1971-1972--Lectures and Related Materials 1938-1972, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - University of Virginia, College of Arts and Sciences, Corcoran Department of History--History 111-112 (517-518): Medieval Civilization, 1938-1977--Lectures and Related Materials--Second Term 1938-1977, (3 folders) (Box 29)
    - History 5-6: Modern European History (1500-1945)--Lectures and Related Materials, Sessions of 1940s-1950s 1940s-1950s, (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Corcoran Department of History--Assignment Sheets and Report Instruction 1940-1970s, (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Class Gradebooks [1946],1949-1977, (3 folders)-[Restricted] (Box 30)
    - History HIEU 817: Medieval Civilization: Outlines on Medieval Law, Feudal and Roman 1973-1975 (Box 30)
    - History 111-112 (517-518): Medieval Civilization, 1938-1977--Lectures and Related Materials--First Term 1938-1977, (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Corcoran Department of History--Course: The Medieval Frontier, 1939-1976, (History 137-138, 817-818, 125-126) Assignments and Examinations 1939-1976 (Box 31)
    - History 110 or 112, 119-120, 222 Medieval Towns--Lectures and Related Materials 1939-1977 (Box 31)
    - Course History C9: Medieval England--once offered; Session of 1942-1943 1942-1943 (Box 31)
    - Course Offerings (once only): History 133, Seminar on Europe Since 1815 (in loco O.J. Hale) 1945--Honors Seminar, ca. 1969? 1945, ca.1969 (Box 31)